As a singer-songwriter,
كوني مغنية وكاتبة أغاني،
people often ask me about my influences or, as I like to call them,
كثيرًا ما يسألني الناس عما يؤثر بي، أو كما أحب أن أسميها،
my sonic lineages.
السلالة الصوتية التي أهتم بها.
And I could easily tell you
أستطيع ببساطة أن أخبركم
that I was shaped by the jazz and hip hop that I grew up with,
إنني ترعرت على موسيقى الجاز وكبرت مع الهيب هوب،
by the Ethiopian heritage of my ancestors,
وميراث أجدادي الإثيوبيين،
or by the 1980s pop on my childhood radio stations.
أو موسيقى الثمانينات التي كنت أسمعها على الإذاعة خلال طفولتي.
But beyond genre, there is another question:
لكن بعيدًا عن النوع الموسيقي، هناك سؤال آخر:
how do the sounds we hear every day influence the music that we make?
كيف تؤثر الأصوات التي نسمعها كل يوم في الموسيقى التي نؤلفها؟
I believe that everyday soundscape
أعتقد أن المشهد الصوتي اليومي
can be the most unexpected inspiration for songwriting,
يمكن أن يكون المصدر الأكثر إلهامًا عند كتابة الأغاني،
and to look at this idea a little bit more closely,
ولكي نتعمق في هذه الفكرة،
I'm going to talk today about three things:
سأتحدث اليوم عن ثلاثة أشياء:
nature, language and silence --
الطبيعة، واللغة، والصمت.
or rather, the impossibility of true silence.
أو بالأحرى، استحالة وجود صمت مطبق.
And through this I hope to give you a sense of a world
ومن خلال ذلك، أرجو أن أمنحكم معنى لعالمٍ
already alive with musical expression,
حي ومفعم بالتعبيرات الموسيقية،
with each of us serving as active participants,
حيث يقوم كلّ منا بدور نشط،
whether we know it or not.
سواء أدركنا ذلك أم لا.
I'm going to start today with nature, but before we do that,
سأبدأ بالتحدث عن الطبيعة، ولكن قبل هذا،
let's quickly listen to this snippet of an opera singer warming up.
فلنستمع بسرعة لهذه المقطوعة حيث يستعد مغني الأوبرا للغناء.
Here it is.
فلنستمع.
(Singing)
(غناء)
(Singing ends)
(نهاية المقطوعة)
It's beautiful, isn't it?
جميل، أليس كذلك؟
Gotcha!
حسنًا!
That is actually not the sound of an opera singer warming up.
ليس هذا صوت مغني أوبرا يستعد للغناء.
That is the sound of a bird
هذا صوت طائر
slowed down to a pace
بوتيرة بطيئة
that the human ear mistakenly recognizes as its own.
تجعل أذن الإنسان تخطئ وتظن أنه صوت إنسان يغني.
It was released as part of Peter Szöke's 1987 Hungarian recording
لقد تم إصدار هذا الصوت ضمن التسجيل الهنغاري لبيتر سوكه سنة 1987
"The Unknown Music of Birds,"
"الموسيقى المجهولة للطيور"
where he records many birds and slows down their pitches
حيث قام بتسجيل أصوات مجموعة من الطيور واعتماد الوتيرة البطيئة
to reveal what's underneath.
ليكتشف ما يكمن وراءها.
Let's listen to the full-speed recording.
لنستمع للتسجيل بسرعته الطبيعية.
(Bird singing)
(عصافير تزقزق)
Now, let's hear the two of them together
الآن، لنستمع إلى التسجيلين معًا
so your brain can juxtapose them.
بحيث يمكن لدماغك المقارنة بينهما.
(Bird singing at slow then full speed)
(عصفور يزقزق ببطء ثم بسرعة عادية)
(Singing ends)
(نهاية المقطع)
It's incredible.
أمر لا يصدق.
Perhaps the techniques of opera singing were inspired by birdsong.
ربما تكون تقنيات غناء الأوبرا قد استُوحيت من غناء العصافير.
As humans, we intuitively understand birds to be our musical teachers.
ونحن كبشر، ندرك بشكل بديهي أن الطيور تعطينا دروسا في الموسيقى.
In Ethiopia, birds are considered an integral part
في إثيوبيا، تُعتبر الطيور جزءً لا يتجزأ
of the origin of music itself.
من جذور الموسيقى ذاتها.
The story goes like this:
وإليكم الحكاية:
1,500 years ago, a young man was born in the Empire of Aksum,
منذ 1500 سنة، وُلد شاب في إمبراطورية أكسوم،
a major trading center of the ancient world.
والتي كانت تُعتبر المركز التجاري قديما.
His name was Yared.
كان يدعى يارد.
When Yared was seven years old his father died,
عندما بلغ يارد السابعة من عمره، توفي والده،
and his mother sent him to go live with an uncle, who was a priest
فأرسلته أمه ليعيش مع عمه، الذي كان قسيسًا
of the Ethiopian Orthodox tradition,
كنيسة التوحيد الأرثوذكسية الإثيوبية،
one of the oldest churches in the world.
والتي تعتبر إحدى أقدم الكنائس في العالم.
Now, this tradition has an enormous amount of scholarship and learning,
تتميز هذه الثقافة بكمٍّ هائل من المنح الدراسية والتعليم،
and Yared had to study and study and study and study,
فكان على يارد أن يدرس ويدرس،
and one day he was studying under a tree,
وكان ذات يوم يدرس تحت شجرة،
when three birds came to him.
عندما حطت 3 عصافير بجانبه.
One by one, these birds became his teachers.
تدريجيا، أصبحت هذه العصافير بمثابة معلمين له.
They taught him music -- scales, in fact.
فقد علموه السلّم الموسيقي.
And Yared, eventually recognized as Saint Yared,
استخدم يارد، الذي أصبح يعرف بالقديس يارد في النهاية،
used these scales to compose five volumes of chants and hymns
هذه السلالم الموسيقية لتأليف 5 أجزاء من الترانيم والأناشيد
for worship and celebration.
للصلاة والاحتفال.
And he used these scales to compose and to create
وقد استعمل هذه السلالم ليؤلف ويضع
an indigenous musical notation system.
نظامًا محليا للتدوين الموسيقي.
And these scales evolved into what is known as kiñit,
وتطورت هذه السلالم لما يعرف بـ"كنيَت"،
the unique, pentatonic, five-note, modal system that is very much alive
النظام الموسيقي الفريد ذي الخمس نقاط، الذي مازال موجودا
and thriving and still evolving in Ethiopia today.
ومازال يتطور في إثيوبيا إلى اليوم.
Now, I love this story because it's true at multiple levels.
أحب هذه القصة لأنها حقيقية على عدة مستويات.
Saint Yared was a real, historical figure,
فالقديس يارد شخصية تاريخية حقيقية،
and the natural world can be our musical teacher.
والعالم الطبيعي يمكن أن يعلمنا الموسيقى.
And we have so many examples of this:
ولدينا أمثلة كثيرة عن هذا:
the Pygmies of the Congo tune their instruments
فأقوام البيجمي في الكونغو يضبطون آلاتهم
to the pitches of the birds in the forest around them.
وفقًا لأصوات طيور في الغابة من حولهم.
Musician and natural soundscape expert Bernie Krause describes
كما يصف الموسيقي وخبير الصوت الطبيعي بيرني كراوس
how a healthy environment has animals and insects
كيف أن البيئة السليمة تعتمد فيها الحيوانات والحشرات
taking up low, medium and high-frequency bands,
وتيرات منخفضة ومتوسطة ومرتفعة،
in exactly the same way as a symphony does.
بنفس الدقة التي تعزف بها الفرق السيمفونية.
And countless works of music were inspired by bird and forest song.
وقد كانت العديد من الأعمال الموسيقية مستوحاة من العصافير وأغاني الغابات.
Yes, the natural world can be our cultural teacher.
نعم، يمكن للعالم الطبيعي أن يتحول إلى معلمنا الثقافي.
So let's go now to the uniquely human world of language.
والآن، دعونا ننتقل إلى عالم اللغة، هذا العالم المحصور بالإنسان.
Every language communicates with pitch to varying degrees,
تتواصل جميع اللغات باعتماد درجات متفاوتة من الطبقات،
whether it's Mandarin Chinese,
سواء كانت لغة المندرين الصينية
where a shift in melodic inflection gives the same phonetic syllable
حيث يعطي التحول في نبرة الصوت للمقطع الصوتي ذاته
an entirely different meaning,
معنى مختلفًا تمامًا،
to a language like English,
أو كانت الإنجليزية،
where a raised pitch at the end of a sentence ...
حيث تعطي الطبقة المرتفعة من الصوت في نهاية الجملة
(Going up in pitch) implies a question?
صيغة السؤال؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
As an Ethiopian-American woman,
بما أنني أمريكية من أصولٍ إثيوبية،
I grew up around the language of Amharic, Amhariña.
فقد نشأت على اللغة الأمهرية.
It was my first language, the language of my parents,
لقد كانت لغتي الأم، لغة والديّ،
one of the main languages of Ethiopia.
وهي إحدى اللغات الرئيسية في إثيوبيا.
And there are a million reasons to fall in love with this language:
ويوجد مليون سبب يجعلني أُغرم بهذه اللغة:
its depth of poetics, its double entendres,
شاعريتها العميقة، وقدرتها على التورية،
its wax and gold, its humor,
أصالتها، وروح الدعابة فيها،
its proverbs that illuminate the wisdom and follies of life.
الأمثال التي تضمها، تظهر حكمة الحياة وحماقاتها.
But there's also this melodicism, a musicality built right in.
ولكن هناك أيضًا ذلك اللحن، والأنغام المتأصّلة فيها.
And I find this distilled most clearly
وأرى ذلك يتجسّد بوضوحٍ
in what I like to call emphatic language --
فيما أدعوه: اللغة التوكيدية.
language that's meant to highlight or underline
اللغة التي تؤكد وتعزز
or that springs from surprise.
أو التي تنبع من المفاجأة.
Take, for example, the word: "indey."
خذوا مثلاً كلمة "إنديه".
Now, if there are Ethiopians in the audience,
لو كان بين الحضور أشخاص من أثيوبيا،
they're probably chuckling to themselves,
لكانوا الآن يضحكون في سرّهم،
because the word means something like "No!"
إذ أن هذه الكلمة تعني "لا!"
or "How could he?" or "No, he didn't."
أو "كيف لها أن تفعل ذلك؟" أو "لا أصدق"
It kind of depends on the situation.
حيث يعتمد المعنى على الظرف والحالة.
But when I was a kid, this was my very favorite word,
عندما كنت طفلة، كانت هذه كلمتي المفضلة،
and I think it's because it has a pitch.
وأعتقد أن السبب يعود لنغمتها.
It has a melody.
يوجد فيه لحن.
You can almost see the shape as it springs from someone's mouth.
يمكن أن ترى تقريبا شكل فم الشخص عندما ينطق به.
"Indey" -- it dips, and then raises again.
"لا"-- ينخفض الصوت ثم يرتفع مرة أخرى.
And as a musician and composer, when I hear that word,
وكموسيقية وملحنة، عندما أسمع هذه الكلمة،
something like this is floating through my mind.
يتبادر إلى ذهني شيء من هذا القبيل.
(Music and singing "Indey")
(موسيقى وغناء "لا")
(Music ends)
(نهاية المقطع)
Or take, for example, the phrase for "It is right" or "It is correct" --
أو لنأخذ، على سبيل المثال، جملة "هذا صحيح" --
"Lickih nehu ... Lickih nehu."
".Lickih nehu ... Lickih nehu"
It's an affirmation, an agreement.
هذا تأكيد، اتفاق.
"Lickih nehu."
".Lickih nehu"
When I hear that phrase,
عندما أسمع هذه العبارة،
something like this starts rolling through my mind.
يتبادر إلى ذهني شيء من هذا القبيل.
(Music and singing "Lickih nehu")
(موسيقى وغناء "Lickih nehu")
(Music ends)
(نهاية المقطع)
And in both of those cases, what I did was I took the melody
وفي كلتا الحالتين، ما فعلته كان أخذ اللحن
and the phrasing of those words and phrases
والصياغة من هذه الكلمات والعبارات
and I turned them into musical parts to use in these short compositions.
وأنا حولتها إلى أجزاء الموسيقية لاستخدامها في هذه المقاطع القصيرة.
And I like to write bass lines,
وأحب اعتماد الصوت المنخفض،
so they both ended up kind of as bass lines.
لذا انتهى بهما المطاف كنوع منه.
Now, this is based on the work of Jason Moran and others
الآن، واستند هذا المقطع على عمل جاسون موران وغيره
who work intimately with music and language,
الذين يعملون بشكل وثيق مع الموسيقى واللغة،
but it's also something I've had in my head since I was a kid,
لكنه أيضا شيء موجود في رأسي منذ كنت طفلة،
how musical my parents sounded
مدى جودة النغمة الموسيقية
when they were speaking to each other and to us.
عندما كان والدايّ يتحدثان لبعضها البعض ولنا.
It was from them and from Amhariña that I learned
تعلمت منهما ومن اللغة الأمهرية
that we are awash in musical expression
أننا مغمورون بتعابير موسيقية
with every word, every sentence that we speak,
مع كل كلمة وكل لجملة نقولها،
every word, every sentence that we receive.
كل كلمة وكل جملة نتلقاها.
Perhaps you can hear it in the words I'm speaking even now.
ربما يمكن سماع ذلك في الكلمات التي أنطق بها الآن.
Finally, we go to the 1950s United States
وأخيرا، نعود إلى عام 1950 في الولايات المتحدة
and the most seminal work of 20th century avant-garde composition:
أكثر عمل بارز في تأليف جريء للقرن 20:
John Cage's "4:33,"
جون كيج "4:33"
written for any instrument or combination of instruments.
كُتب من أجل أي آلة أو مجموعة من الآلات.
The musician or musicians are invited to walk onto the stage
الموسيقي أو الموسيقيين مدعوون للمشي على خشبة المسرح
with a stopwatch and open the score,
مع ساعة توقيت والافتتاح،
which was actually purchased by the Museum of Modern Art --
والتي تم شراؤها في الواقع من قبل متحف الفن الحديث -
the score, that is.
هذا هو الافتتاح.
And this score has not a single note written
ولا يوجد فيه أي نوتة موسيقية مكتوبة
and there is not a single note played
ولم تُعزف نوتة موسيقية واحدة
for four minutes and 33 seconds.
لمدة اربع دقائق و 33 ثانية.
And, at once enraging and enrapturing,
وما إن تنتهي الإثارة والبهجة،
Cage shows us that even when there are no strings
يظهر لنا أنه عندما لا توجد آلات وترية
being plucked by fingers or hands hammering piano keys,
تعزف عليها أو يدٍ تنقرعلى مفاتيح البيانو
still there is music,
لاتزال هناك موسيقى،
still there is music.
لاتزال هناك موسيقى.
And what is this music?
ماهي هذه الموسيقى؟
It was that sneeze in the back.
يوجد صوت عطاسٍ في الخلف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It is the everyday soundscape that arises from the audience themselves:
هذا هو المشهد اليومي الذي يظهر من الجمهور أنفسهم:
their coughs, their sighs, their rustles, their whispers, their sneezes,
السعال والتنهد والحفيف والهمس والعطس،
the room, the wood of the floors and the walls
الغرفة وخشب الأرضيات
expanding and contracting, creaking and groaning
والتوسع والانكماش، الصرير والأنين
with the heat and the cold,
مع الحرارة والبرد،
the pipes clanking and contributing.
صوت الأنابيب والمساهمة.
And controversial though it was, and even controversial though it remains,
ومثير للجدل رغم كونه كذلك، وحتى مثيرا للجدل مع أنه لازال موجودا،
Cage's point is that there is no such thing as true silence.
هدف كايج هو أنه لا يوجد صمت بالفعل.
Even in the most silent environments, we still hear and feel the sound
حتى في أكثر البيئات الصامتة، ما زلنا نسمع الصوت ونشعر به
of our own heartbeats.
صوت دقات قلبنا.
The world is alive with musical expression.
العالم مفعم بالتعابير الموسيقية.
We are already immersed.
نحن محاطون بذلك.
Now, I had my own moment of, let's say, remixing John Cage
الآن، كان لي لحظة خاصة، دعنا نقول، تعديل لجون كيج
a couple of months ago
منذ عدة أشهر
when I was standing in front of the stove cooking lentils.
عندما كنت واقفة أمام الموقد أطهو شربة العدس.
And it was late one night and it was time to stir,
وكان الوقت متأخر تلك الليلة وحان وقت الإثارة،
so I lifted the lid off the cooking pot,
لذلك رفعت الغطاء عن وعاء الطبخ،
and I placed it onto the kitchen counter next to me,
ووضعته على طاولة المطبخ المجاور لي،
and it started to roll back and forth
وبدأت تتشقلب
making this sound.
وإصدار هذا الصوت.
(Sound of metal lid clanking against a counter)
(صوت قعقعة غطاء معدني على طاولة المطبخ)
(Clanking ends)
(نهاية المقطع)
And it stopped me cold.
وأوقفني ذلك البرود.
I thought, "What a weird, cool swing that cooking pan lid has."
فكرت: "يا له من صوت غريب، الذي أصدره غطاء الطبخ المتأرجح"
So when the lentils were ready and eaten,
عندما أصبحت شربة العدس جاهزة وتم تناولها،
I hightailed it to my backyard studio,
انسحبت باتجاه الاستديو الخلفي،
and I made this.
وقمت بتسجيل هذا.
(Music, including the sound of the lid, and singing)
(موسيقى، تضم صوت الغطاء وغناء)
(Music ends)
(نهاية المقطع)
Now, John Cage wasn't instructing musicians
لم يكن جون كايج يأمر الموسيقيين
to mine the soundscape for sonic textures to turn into music.
تفجير المنظر الموسيقي لتتحول بنية صوتية إلى موسيقى.
He was saying that on its own,
كان يقول أن البيئة من تلقاء نفسها
the environment is musically generative,
تولّد الموسيقى
that it is generous, that it is fertile,
أن هذا أمر سخي ومنتج،
that we are already immersed.
أننا محاطون بذلك بالفعل.
Musician, music researcher, surgeon and human hearing expert Charles Limb
الموسيقي، والباحث الموسيقي، الجراح وخبير السمع تشارلز ليمب
is a professor at Johns Hopkins University
هو أستاذ في جامعة جونز هوبكنز
and he studies music and the brain.
ويدرس الموسيقى والدماغ.
And he has a theory
يملك نظرية تقول
that it is possible -- it is possible --
أنه من الممكن-- من الممكن--
that the human auditory system actually evolved to hear music,
أن النظام السمعي البشري تطور بالفعل لسماع الموسيقى،
because it is so much more complex than it needs to be for language alone.
لأنه أكثر تعقيدا من أجل الحاجة لللغة فقط،
And if that's true,
إذا كان ذلك صحيحا،
it means that we're hard-wired for music,
هذا يعني أننا مرتبطون بالموسيقى بشكل دائمٍ،
that we can find it anywhere,
أننا يمكننا إيجادها في أي مكانٍ،
that there is no such thing as a musical desert,
أنه لا يوجد شيء مثل صحراء الموسيقى،
that we are permanently hanging out at the oasis,
أننا نتنزه باستمرار في الواحة،
and that is marvelous.
وهذا أمر مدهشٌ.
We can add to the soundtrack, but it's already playing.
يمكننا أن نضيف الموسيقى التصويرية، وهي موجودة بالفعل.
And it doesn't mean don't study music.
وهذا لا يعني عدم دراسة الموسيقى.
Study music, trace your sonic lineages and enjoy that exploration.
ادرس الموسيقى، وضَعْ نوتاتك الصوتية الخاصة واستمتع بالاكتشاف.
But there is a kind of sonic lineage to which we all belong.
لكنه يوجد نسب صوتي ننحدر منه جميعا.
So the next time you are seeking percussion inspiration,
لذا في المرة القادمة التي تبحث فيها عن إلهامٍِ نقري،
look no further than your tires, as they roll over the unusual grooves
انظر إلى ما ليس أبعد من إطارات السيارة، كما تدور بشكل روتيني غريب
of the freeway,
على الطريق السريع،
or the top-right burner of your stove
أو الشعلة الموجودة أعلى يمين الموقد،
and that strange way that it clicks
والطريقة الغريبة التي تنقر بها
as it is preparing to light.
كأنها تستعد لتُنير.
When seeking melodic inspiration,
عندما تبحث عن إلهام لحني،
look no further than dawn and dusk avian orchestras
لا تنظر إلى أبعد من أوركسترا الطيور عند الفجر والغسق
or to the natural lilt of emphatic language.
أو إلى الإيقاع الطبيعي للغة الرائعة.
We are the audience and we are the composers
نحن الجمهور ونحن الملحنون
and we take from these pieces
ونقتبس من هذه القطع
we are given.
التي تقدم لنا.
We make, we make, we make, we make,
نكتب، ونألف ونفعل ذلك،
knowing that when it comes to nature or language or soundscape,
علما أنه عندما يتعلق الأمر بالطبيعة أو اللغة أو المنظر الصوتي،
there is no end to the inspiration --
لا يوجد نهاية للإلهام -
if we are listening.
إذا كنا نستمع لذلك.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)